CURRICULUM VITAE



AVANISH PRATAP SINGH

e-mail: <u>avi.pratap2007@gmail.com</u> <u>apsingh@gvtindia.org</u>

Contact: +91-8802445969

Current Address:

A-601, KRIBHCO Township Plot No. 122, Sector 35 NOIDA (UP) – 201301

Permanent Address:

148/A, Old Maal Godam Road, Sahodarpur West, Pratapgarh Uttar Pradesh – 230 001

Personal Details:

Father's Name : Mr. H. B. Singh **Date of Birth** : 17/01/1987

Gender : Male **Marital Status** : Married

Languages Known: Hindi, English

Objective

To utilize my skill as GIS, Remote sensing and Environment related fields, correspondence in an optimum way for growing with the organization and accomplish its goals through personal as well as team commitment.

Profile Summary

Good exposure and practical experience in a range of Spatial & Non-Spatial data utilization, Satellite Image Processing, Interpretation and Analysis with emphasis on Forestry, Geology, Natural Resources, Disaster Management, Utility & Facility Management & Urban Planning etc. Good experience of Image processing & Geographical Information System software particularly in ERDAS IMAGINE and Arc GIS.

Work Experience and Responsibilities

- GIS Specialist in Gramin Vikas Trust (supported by KRIBHCO), Noida, U.P. under IWMP projects for Haryana, Maharashtra and Odisha state for Monitoring and Impact Evaluation of Watershed projects in terms of changes in Biophysical parameters using Remote Sensing and GIS based assessment techniques. (01.06.2015 to Present)
- Research Assistant in Centre for Policy Studies, New Delhi under "Madhya Pradesh Resource Atlas Programme"; commissioned by MP Council of Science & Technology, Bhopal. (01.12.2011 to 30.05.2015)
 - Compiling, analyzing, processing and graphically presenting large amounts of information and data to create a resource atlas for every district of Madhya Pradesh.
 - Extracting of information from Satellite Imageries such as IRS-1C/1D, P6 & Resourcesat-2, LISS III & LISS IV data with the help of field survey & classification for various thematic mapping (Land Use & Land Cover) of many districts of Madhya Pradesh.
 - Prepared GIS based Web Portal of Tribal School Information for 21 Districts of Madhya Pradesh.
 - Data collection, editing, analysis and final map compilation in GIS environment.
- Worked as XML Programmer in field of XML Programing in multinational e-publishing company Aptara International Pvt. Ltd. (Techbooks), New Delhi. (05.05.2008 to 08.11.2009)
 - Conversion of LaTex and Doc source file into XML Code in the style provided by the Client (Blackwell- Journals) to produce quality page output for printing & internet content.

Education

Barkatullah University, Bhopal (M.P.)

Degree: M. Sc.

Major: **Geoinformatics** 70.65 %

Passing Year: 2011

Mahatma Gandhi Chitrakoot Gramodaya University, Chitrakoot, Satna (M.P.)

Degree: B. Sc. (HONS.)

Major: **Information Technology Application** 67.50 % (6.8/10 CGPA)

Passing Year: 2008

Computer/Software Knowledge

GIS Software : ArcGIS 10 & 9.3.1 and ArcGIS SERVER 9.3.1

Image Processing Software : ERDAS Imagine 11 & 9.1

Open Source Technology : Map Server & Quantum- GIS (Q-GIS)

Web Development Languages : XML & HTML

Graphics Software : Adobe Illustrator 10 & Quark Express 5.0

M. Sc. Project Work

"Web-GIS Based Navigation Information System" using ArcGIS Server from Reliance Tech. Services - GIS, Bhopal (M.P.) duration of 6 months.

Project Work Description

Developed an application based on Network Analysis operations in ArcGIS using advance geoprocessing capability/modeling and migrated this desktop-based application towards web-based platform on ArcGIS Server for online Navigation Information System.

Publication in Journal

Singh, Avanish Pratap, Sharaddeep and Goyal, Sandeep., (2014) "Web GIS based Navigation Information System using Network Anolysis capability: A Web GIS Approach". **Anveshanam: Issues of Journal of Computer Science & Application**. Vol. III, No. 1, August 2014-July 2015.

Oral and Poster Paper Presentation

- ➤ Singh Avanish Pratap et al. "Open Source GIS Technology for Web based Navigation Information System" accepted for poster presentation in National Symposium on 'Empowering Rural India through Space Technology' organized by Indian Society of Remote Sensing (ISRS) 2011 as Student Nominee behalf of ISRS Bhopal Chapter.
- Singh Avanish Pratap, Sharaddeep & Singhai Akinchan "Web GIS based Shortest-Route Searching System for Bhopal City" accepted for poster presentation in National Symposium on 'Empowering Rural India through Space Technology' organized by Indian Society of Remote Sensing (ISRS) 2011.

Contribution in Resource Atlas Preparation

"Datia Resource Atlas (ISBN: 81-86041-38-9)" as Contributor, published jointly by Madhya Pradesh Council of Science & Technology, Bhopal and Centre for Policy Studies, New Delhi. This atlas book is a 247 pages publication depicting the Resource Strengths of Datia District in the form of various Primary Maps, Secondary Maps, Demography Graphs, Charts and Tables.

Training

- Working on Web development of **Sericulture Information Linkages and Knowledge System (SILKS)** for 6 districts of Madhya Pradesh at **North Eastern Space Application Centre, Umiam, Meghalaya**.
- ➤ 2 months "EDUSAT Based training in RS, GIS & GPS" organized by IIRS, Dehradun.
- > 12 days training in "ADVANCES IN GEOINFORMATICS" organized by IIRS, Dehradun.
- 2 days training program on ERDAS Professional, Vector & Virtual GIS by Intergraph, Gurgaon at MP Council of Science & Technology, Bhopal.
- **EDUSAT** based Training on "Hyper spectral Remote Sensing" organized by IIRS, Dehradun.
- ➢ Pre-Symposium Tutorial on "Open Source Geospatial Software and Resources" held at M.P. Council of Science and Technology, Bhopal during November 06-07, 2011 organized by Indian Society of Remote Sensing (ISRS).
- 45 days training in Web Designing (using HTML, DHTML & XML) from NIPS Computer Institute, Allahabad.

Conference/Workshop

- Participation in 'Global Indian Scientist and Technocrats Convention' on "Scientific and Technological Approaches for Sustainable use of Water Resources" held at M.E.S. Abasaheb Garware College, Pune.
- ➤ 3 days training workshop on "Water Conservation techniques" organized by "Indian Science Congress Association", Bhopal Chapter.
- **2** days **National Workshop** on "**Applications of Geoinformatics for Sustainable Rural Development and Management**" held at Mahatma Gandhi Chitrakoot Gramodaya Vishwavidyala, Chitrakoot, Satna (M.P.).
- As part of regular activities **10 days** (120 hours) working as a member of **National Service Scheme (NSS)** at University Agriculture Form House, M.G.C.G.V, Chitrakoot, Satna (M.P.).

References

Mr. Subrata Bhattacharya

Chief Manager (M&E-BD) Gramin Vikas Trust (GVT) 5th Floor, 'A' Wing, KRIBHCO Bhawan A-10, Sector 1, Noida (UP) 201301

Contact: +91-9953140813

e-mail: s.bhattacharyya@gvtindia.org

Dr. J. K. Bajaj

Director Centre for Policy Studies New Delhi 110 060

Contact: +91-9811308697 e-mail: jatinderkbajaj@gmail.com Dr. Sandeep Goyal

Principal Scientist & Head MP Resource Atlas Division (MPRA) MP Council of Science & Technology Bhopal (M.P.) 462 003

Contact: +91-9425370195 e-mail: sgoyalbsg@gmail.com